# LAXMIKANT LP PATHADE

http://laxmikantpathade.com • (315)560-8200 • lpathade@syr.edu 4-023, Center for Science and Technology, Syracuse University, Syracuse NY 13244

## Summary

Resourceful materials researcher with 8+ years of training under belt, 4+ years of facility administrator experience, exceptional work-ethic, team player with strong written and oral communications skills.

Expert in materials research, wet-lab syntheses, structural characterization, electron microscopy, spectroscopy, computational analysis, technical softwares, & computers.

### Work & Research Experience

### Administrator at the X-ray Facility at Syracuse University

2014-present

- Oversaw day to day operations of the powder X-ray diffractometer at the X-ray facility at SU. Saved university ~\$60,000 per year in instrument manager pay by taking over that position in addition to my research & teaching duties.
- Responsible for new user training, queue management, specialized sample prep & data analysis, instrument troubleshooting, Haskris/chiller upkeep, scheduling maintenance & regulatory inspections.

#### Graduate Researcher at Syracuse University

2013-present

- My research focuses on synthesis of transition metal nanoparticles (NPs) that exhibited hollow internal microstructures.
- We successfully exploited our findings to improve corrosion resistance in these NPs and create truly "stainless" NPs.
- Other research topics included Asymmetric Internal Voids in Novel NP Systems, Silica Coating & Surface Functionalization of Magnetic NPs, Reaction Monitoring using CsPbX<sub>3</sub> Perovskites, & DDA Computation Routines
- Published 6+ peer reviewed journal articles, co-authored 2 patents, and presented my work in 5+ conferences.

# Teaching Assistant at Syracuse University

2013-present

- Taught General Chemistry and Honors General Chemistry (CHE 107-117, CHE 129) courses at SU. Held recitations & office hours, conducted labs, & reported student progress.
- Developed 4 new lab modules to introduce advanced materials chemistry topics such as synthesis & properties of NPs.

#### **Industrial Internships**

• Worked on a research project for a Fortune 500 chemical company in major capacity.

2017

• Interned at 2 medium-sized pigment-manufacturing plants in the industrial area near Mumbai, India.

2012

• Observed unit operations of chemical engineering, and prepared a report on manufacturing efficiency & workplace safety.

# EDUCATION

#### Syracuse University

2013-2018

PhD Candidate in Materials Chemistry with Prof. Mathew M. Maye

Thesis: Internal Morphology & Corrosion Resistance in Stainless Steel Nanoparticles

### Institute of Chemical Technology, Mumbai

2009-2013

Bachelor of Technology in Chemistry; Minors in Chemical Engineering & Organic Colorants

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Chemical Synthesis: Nanoparticles (Transition and Noble Metals, Perovskites, Quantum Dots) · Schlenk Line and Glovebox techniques · Microwave · Organic Lab work
- Structural Characterization: Powder and Single Crystal XRD (Currently work as facility admin)
- Electron Microscopy: TEM / HR-TEM (trained on 3 different JEOL TEMs; trained new users) · EDS (Oxford Instruments Certification) · STEM · SEM · AFM (Bruker Innova) · Optical
- Spectroscopy: XPS/ESCA · EDS · NMR · Raman · AA · Mass · FTIR · UV-Vis · PL
- Technical Misc.: Magnetization in materials · Cyclic Voltammetry · DLS-  $\zeta$  potential · Ultracentrifuge · Sputter Coater · Spin coater · Photolithography · TGA · DSC · Vernier Modules · Rotovap
- Computational Analysis: Discrete Dipole Approximation (DDA) · Familiar with FDTD
- $\bullet \ \, \textbf{Softwares} \colon \, \text{Datagraph} \cdot \text{Plotly} \cdot \text{Origin} \cdot \text{ImageJ} \cdot \text{ChemDraw} \cdot \text{Vesta} \cdot \text{TEMCON} \, (\text{JEOL}) \cdot \text{Digital Micrograph} \, (\text{Gatan}) \\ \cdot \, \text{AZtec} \, \left( \text{Oxford Instr.} \right) \cdot \text{Bruker Diffrac.Suite} \cdot \text{CasaXPS} \cdot \text{Adobe Illustrator} \cdot \text{Corel-Draw} \cdot \text{Maya basics}$
- Languages: Python · Jekyll · HTML/Markdown · Hindi · Marathi · Familiar with C/C++, Fortran
- Computer Misc.: 3D-printing · Raspberry Pi · Linux · Wordpress/MAMP · LATEX· git